This is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in the public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
the wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter 15 The Discovery of Oz, the
Terrible The four travelers walked up to the great gate of Emerald City and rang
at the bell. After ringing several times, it was opened by the same Guardian of
the Gates they had met before.
“What! are you back again?” he asked and surprised Do you not see us?” answered the
Scarecrow. “But I thought you had gone to visit the Wicked Witch of the West.” “We
did visit her,” said the Scarecrow. “And she let you go again?”
asked the man and wonder. “She could not help it, for she is melted,” explained the
Scarecrow. “Melted! Well, that is good news, indeed,” said the man. “Who melted her?” “It
was Dorothy,” said the Lion gravely. “Good gracious!” exclaimed the man, and he bowed
very low indeed before her. Then he led them into his little room and locked the
spectacles from the great box on all their eyes, just as she had done before.
Afterward they passed on through the gate into the Emerald City. When the
people heard from the Guardian of the Gates that Dorothy had melted the Wicked
Witch of the West, they all gathered around the travelers and followed them in a great crowd to
the Palace of Oz. The soldier with the green whiskers was still on guard before
the door, but he let them in at once, and they were again met by the beautiful
green girl, who showed each of them to their old rooms at once, so they might
rest until the Great wizard was ready to receive them. The soldier had the news
carried straight to Oz that Dorothy and the other travelers had come back again,
after destroying the Wicked Witch; but Oz made no reply. They thought the Great
Wizard would send for them at once, but he did not. They had no word from him the
next day, nor the next, nor the next. The waiting was tiresome and wearing, and at
last they grew vex that Oz should treat them in so poor a fashion, after sending
them to undergo hardships in slavery. So the Scarecrow at last asked the green girl to take
another message to Oz, saying if he did not let them in to see him at once they
would call the Winged Monkeys to help them, and find out whether he kept his
promises or not. When the Wizard was given this message he was so frightened
that he sent word for them to come to the Throne Room at four minutes after
nine o’clock the next morning. He had once met the Winged Monkeys in the Land
of the West, and he did not wish to meet them again. The four travelers passed the
sleepless night, each thinking of the gift Oz had promised to bestow on him. Dorothy fell
asleep only once, and then she dreams she was in Kansas, where Aunt Em was telling
her how glad she was to have her little girl home again. Promptly at nine o’clock
the next morning the green whiskered soldier came to them, and four minutes
later they all went into the Throne Room of the Great Oz. Of course each one of
them expected to see the Wizard in the shape he had taken before, and all were
greatly surprised when they looked about and saw no one at all in the room. They
kept close to the door and closer to one another, for the stillness of the empty
room was more dreadful than any of the forms they had seen Oz take. Presently
they heard a solemn Voice, that seemed to come somewhere near the top of the great
dome, and it said: “I am Oz, the Great and Terrible. Why do you seek me?” They looked
again in every part of the room, and then, seeing no one, Dorothy asked, “Where are
you?” “I am everywhere,” answered the Voice, “but to the eyes of the common mortals I
am invisible. I will now seat myself upon my throne, that you may converse with me.”
Indeed, the Voice seemed just then to come straight from the throne itself; so
they walked toward it and stood in a row while Dorothy said: “We have come to claim
our promise paws What promise?” asked Oz.
“You promised to send me back to Kansas when the Wicked Witch was destroyed,” said
the girl. “And you promised to give me brains,” said the Scarecrow. “And you
promised to give me a heart,” said the Tin Woodman.
“And you promised to give me courage,” said the Cowardly Lion. “Is the Wicked which
really destroyed?” asked the Voice, and Dorothy thought it trembled a little. “Yes,”
she answered, “I melted her with a bucket of water.” “Dear me,” said the Voice,
“how sudden! Well, come to me tomorrow, for I must have time to think it over.”
“You’ve had plenty of time already,” said the Tin Woodman angrily. “We shan’t wait a
day longer,” said the Scarecrow. “You must keep your promise to us!” exclaimed
Dorothy. The Lion thought it might be as well to frighten the Wizard, so he gave a
large, loud war which was so fierce and dreadful that Toto jumped away from him
an alarm and tipped over the screen that stood in the corner. As it fell with a
crash they looked that way in the next moment all of them were filled with
wonder. For they saw, standing in just the spot the screen had hidden, a little old
man, with a bald head and a wrinkled face, who seemed to be as much surprised as
they were. The Tin Woodman, raising his axe, rushed toward the little man and
cried out, “Who are you?” “I am Oz, the Great and Terrible,” said the little man, in a
trembling voice. “But don’t strike me— —please don’t— —and I’ll do anything you
want me to.” Our friends looked at him in surprise and dismay.
“I thought Oz was a great Head,” said Dorothy. “And I thought Oz was a lovely
Lady,” said the Scarecrow. “And I thought Oz was a terrible Beast,” said the Tin
Woodman. “And I thought Oz was a Ball of Fire,” exclaimed the Lion. “No, you are all
wrong to the little man meekly. “I have been making believe.” “Making believe!” cried
Dorothy. “Are you not a Great Wizard?” “Hush, my dear Don’t speak so loud, or you will
be overheard— —and I should be ruined. I’m supposed to be a Great Wizard.” “And you
aren't she asked. “Not a bit of it, my dear
just a common man.” “You’re more than that,” said the Scarecrow, in a grieved tone;
“you’re a humbug.” “Exactly so!” declared the little man, rubbing his hands together as
if it pleased him. “I am a humbug.” “But this is terrible,” said the Tin Woodman. “How
shall I ever get my heart?” “Or I my courage as the Lion. “Or I my brains?”
wailed the Scarecrow, wiping the tears from his eyes with his coat-sleeve
My dear friends,” said eyes I pray you not speak of these little things. Think of me,
and the terrible trouble I am in at being found out.” “Doesn’t anyone else know
you’re a humbug?” asked Dorothy. “No one knows it but you for and myself,” replied
Oz. “I have fooled everyone so long that I thought I should never be found out. It
was a great mistake my ever letting you into the Throne Room. Usually I will not
see even my subjects, and so they believe I am something terrible.” “But, I don’t
understand,” said Dorothy, in bewilderment.
“How was it that you appeared to me as a great Head?” “That was one of my tricks,”
answered Oz. “Step this way, please, and I will tell you all about it.” He led the
way to a small chamber in the rear of the Throne Room, and they all followed
him. He pointed to one corner, in which lay the great Head, made out of many
thicknesses of paper, and with a carefully painted face. “This I hung from
the ceiling by a wire,” said Oz. “I stood behind the screen and pulled a thread, to
make the eyes move in the mouth open.” “But how about the voice?” she inquired. “Oh I'm
a ventriloquist,” said the little man.
“I can throw the sound of my voice wherever I wish, so that you thought it
was coming out of the Head. Here are the other things I used to deceive you.” He
showed the Scarecrow the dress and the mask he had worn when he seemed to be
the lovely Lady. And the Tin Woodman saw that his terrible Beast was nothing but
a lot of skins, sewn together, with slats to keep their sides out. As for the Ball
of Fire, the false Wizard had hung that also from the ceiling. It was really a
ball of cotton, but when oil was poured upon it the ball burned fiercely. “Really,”
said the Scarecrow, “you ought to be ashamed of yourself
for being such a humbug.” “I am— —I certainly am,” answered the little man sorrowfully;
“but it was the only thing I could do.
Sit down, please, there are plenty of chairs; and I will tell you my story.” So
they sat down and listened while he told the following tale. “I was born in Omaha—”
“Why, that isn’t very far from Kansas!” cried Dorothy. “No, but it’s farther from
here,” he said, shaking his head at her sadly. “When I grew up I became a
ventriloquist, and at that I was very well trained by a great master. I can
imitate any kind of bird or beast.” Here he mewed so like a kitten that Toto
pricked up his ears and looked everywhere to see where she was. “After a
time,” continued Oz, “I tired of that, and became a balloonist.” “What is that?” asked
Dorothy. “A man who goes up in a balloon
on circus day, so as to draw a crowd of people together and get them to pay to
see the circus,” he explained. “Oh,” she said, “I know.” “Well, one day I went up in a
balloon and the ropes got twisted, so that I couldn’t come down again. It went
way up above the clouds, so far that a current of air struck it and carried it
many, many miles away. For a day in the night I traveled through the air, and on
the morning of the second day I awoke and found the balloon floating over a
strange and beautiful country. “It came down gradually, and I was not hurt a bit.
But I found myself in the midst of a strange people, who, seeing me come from
the clouds, thought I was a great Wizard.
Of course I let them think so, because they were afraid of me, and promised to
do anything I wish them to do Just to amuse myself, and keep the good people
busy, I ordered them to build the City, and my Palace; and they did it all
willingly and well. Then I thought, as the country was so green and beautiful, I
would call it the Emerald City; and to make the name fit her better I put green
spectacles on all the people, so that everything they saw was green.” “But isn’t
everything here green that's Dorothy. “No more than in any other city,” replied Oz;
“but when you wear green spectacles, why of course everything you see looks green to you.
The Emerald City was built a great many years ago, for I was a young man when the
balloon brought me here, and I am a very old man now. But my people have worn
green glasses on their eyes so long that most of them think it really is an
Emerald City, and it certainly is a beautiful place, abounding in jewels and
precious metals, and every good thing that is needed to make one happy. I have been
good to the people, and they like me; but ever since this Palace was built, I have
shut myself up and would not see any of them. “One of my greatest fears was the
Witches, for while I had no magical powers at all I soon found out that the
Witches were really able to do wonderful things. There were four of them in this
country, and they ruled the people who lived in the North and South and East and West.
Fortunately, the Witches of the North and South were good, and I knew they would do
me no harm; but the Witches of the East and the West were terribly wicked, and
had they not thought I was more powerful than they themselves, they would surely
have destroyed me. As it was, I lived in deadly fear of them for many years; so
you can imagine how pleased I was when I heard your house had fallen on the
Wicked Witch of the East. When you came to me, I was willing to promise you
anything if you would only do away with the other Witch; but, now that you have
melted her I'm ashamed to say that I cannot keep my promises.” “I think you are
a very bad man,” said Dorothy. “Oh, no, my dear;
I’m really a very good man, but I’m a
very bad Wizard, I must admit.” “Can’t you give me brains?” asked the Scarecrow. “You
don’t need them. You were learning something every day. A baby has brains,
but it doesn’t know much. Experience is the only thing that brings knowledge, and
the longer you are on earth the more experience you were sure to get.” “That may
all be true,” said the Scarecrow, “but I shall be very unhappy unless you give me
brains.” The false Wizard looked at him carefully. “Well,” he said with a sigh, “I’m
not much of a magician, as I said; but if you will come to me tomorrow morning, I
will stuff your head with brains. I cannot tell you how to use them, however;
you must find that out for yourself.” “Oh, thank you— —thank you!” cried the Scarecrow.
“I’ll find a way to use them, never fear!” “But how about my courage?” asked the Lion
anxiously. “You have plenty of courage I'm sure,” answered Oz. “All you need is
confidence in yourself. There is no living thing that is not afraid when it
faces danger. The True courage is facing danger when you are afraid, and
that kind of courage you have in plenty.” “Perhaps I have, but I’m scared just the
same,” said the Lion. “I shall really be very unhappy unless you give me the sort
of courage that makes one forget he is afraid.” “Very well, I will give you that
sort of courage tomorrow,” replied Oz. “How about my heart?” asked the Tin Woodman. “Why
ask for that,” answered Oz, “I think you are wrong to want a heart. It makes most
people unhappy. If you only knew it, you are in luck not to have a heart.” “That
must be a matter of opinion,” said that Tin Woodman. “For my part, I will bear all
the unhappiness without a murmur, if you will give me the heart.” “Very well,”
answered Oz meekly. “Come to me tomorrow and you shall have a heart. I have played
Wizard for so many years that I may as well continue the part a little longer.”
“And now,” said Dorothy, “how am I to get back to Kansas?” “We shall have to think
about that,” replied the little man. “Give me two or three days to consider the
matter and I’ll try to find a way to carry you over the desert. In the
meantime you shall all be treated as my guests, and while you live in the Palace
my people will wait upon you and obey your slightest wish. There is only one
thing I ask in return for my help— —such that it is. You must keep my secret
until no one I am a humbug.” They agreed to say nothing of what they had learned,
and went back to their rooms in high spirits. Even Dorothy had hoped that “The
Great and Terrible Humbug,” as she had called him, would find a way to send her
back to Kansas, and if he did she was willing to forgive him everything end of